<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Black Representation in Black Panther</title>
            <title type="sub">Digital Edition 2</title>
            <author>
<persName xml:id="SIC">Sophia Isabella Crooks</persName>
<persName xml:id="KLG">Kayla LeRose Graham</persName>
<orgName xml:id="AADHum">African American History, Culture, an Digital Humanities (AADHum)</orgName>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>TEI template provided by</resp>
              <persName>Jessica Lu</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
<resp>Encoded by</resp>
<persName ref="SIC">Sophia Crooks</persName>
<persName ref="KLG">Kayla Graham</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>
        <orgName ref="AADHum">African American History, Culture, an Digital Humanities (AADHum)</orgName>
           </publisher>
<pubPlace>
  <settlement>College Park</settlement>
  <region>Maryland</region>
          </pubPlace>
          <date when="2018-05-02">May 2, 2018</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
<title type="main">Black Panther let me see myself as a superhero for the first time</title>
<title type="sub">Marvel has finally used its power for the good of representation</title>
<publisher>
<orgName>Vox Media</orgName>
</publisher>
<author>
  <persName xml:id="AF">Allegra Frank</persName>
</author>
<pubPlace ref="https://www.polygon.com/2018/2/26/17030036/black-panther-representation-in-hollywood-opinion">
<settlement>New York City</settlement>
<region>New York</region>
<settlement>Washington D.C.</settlement><!-- There are two headquater locations for this publisher. That is why we decided to list two settlement tags and one region tag. -->
</pubPlace>
<date when="2018-02-26">February 26, 2018</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Originally prepared for the purpose of amplifying the voice of this author and her opinions on the film, Black Panther.</p>
<p>This article was encoded because of the particular language that the author uses to describe a variety of different aspects of the film. She uses this language to discuss the large amount of black represenation and black hairstyles. She also uses this particular language to describe how the characters celebrate their own blackness. </p>
</projectDesc>
<samplingDecl>
<p>The three pictures that the author of this piece decided to input have been retained. We believe that these pictures are important to the author in that they elicit different emotions (admiration, satisfation (with representation), proudness(of blackness)) that she expreesses through her use of language throughout the text. </p>
</samplingDecl>
<editorialDecl>
  <normalization>
<p>There were a large number of advertisements present throughout this article that we decided to omit. This is due to the fact that these advertisments have nothing to do with the text and take away from the importance of a digital text that describes the black representation in Black Panther.</p>
<p>hyperlinks</p>
  </normalization>
</editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text>
      <body>
<figure><graphic url="https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/bk4DRQdjaABp8S4m0ZPvqYf_yns=/0x0:5784x3855/920x613/filters:focal(2430x1466:3354x2390):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_image/image/58824809/BlackPanther596d2f0c153d1.0.jpg"></graphic><figDesc>This photo shows Lupita Nyong'o's character, Nakia, and Chadwick Boseman's character, T'Challa, walking down a flight of stairs during a scene in the film. They both stand out from the rest of the people in this photo because of their futuristic African-inspired clothing.</figDesc></figure>
<p>
  Calling Black Panther one of the most important films I’ve ever seen definitely sounds overdramatic. But this isn’t hyperbolic, and I’m not alone in saying this. For what feels like the first time, an <seg type="black-representation">entire group of people that look like me</seg> — <seg type="black-representation">like many of us</seg> — get to be the heroes in a big-budget, massively successful film. And there’s no hiding who they are or where they’re from in Black Panther; they’re <trait type="physical"><label>ethnicity</label><desc>African</desc></trait>, and <seg type="celebration-of-blackness">they’re proud of it.</seg>
</p> <!-- The celebration of blackness analysis tag was used to identify the language that the author uses to express her appreciation for how proud the characters of Black Panther were of their culture, background, and blackness.   -->
<p>
  Superhero movies are, by design, wish fulfillment: We want their powers! We want their invincibility! We want their fame! We want their abs! (We wouldn’t dare wearing spandex otherwise.) I obviously wish I had a body like <persName>Black Widow’s</persName> or the bank account of <persName>Tony Stark</persName>, and I can relate to <persName>Peter Parker’s</persName> anxiety. Yet as a woman of color, <seg type="lack-of-representaton">I’ve struggled to find myself</seg> in any <orgName>Marvel</orgName> movie to date, even while dutifully paying up to see them every few months like an average member of society.
</p> <!-- The lack of representation analysis tag has to do with the language we identified as representation and lack there of. The author uses this language to describe the lack of representation that she felt as a fan of superhero movies.-->
<p>
  We’ve seen <orgName>Marvel Comics</orgName> be <seg type="black-representation">better about letting minority characters suit up</seg>; even <persName>Iron Man</persName> became a <seg type="black-representation">teenage African-American girl</seg> recently. But as <orgName>Vulture</orgName> noted back in 2013, ahead of the premiere of Thor: The Dark World, there continues to be a divide between the comic book and film sides of the company. <seg type="lack-of-representation">What few people of color there are tend to be villains or supporting cast members, not the heroes on the poster</seg>. That lack of representation is meaningful, even if it doesn’t seem to affect box office numbers. (<seg type="lack-of-representation">The Avengers, with a total of one <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>black</desc></trait> person and one woman in the main cast, remains one of the highest-grossing films of all time</seg>, after all.)
</p> <!-- The black representation analysis tag identifies the language that the author uses to describe her satisfaction with the amount of black represenation in the film. She expresses this satisfaction in a variety of ways, yet it all used to describe the representation of black characters, with roles that black characters usually do not play.  -->
<figure><graphic url="https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/ZFjm-egEU6UIBezN5p9s00A4rwg=/0x0:5350x3567/720x0/filters:focal(0x0:5350x3567):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/10165683/BlackPanther5a544af14a477.jpg"></graphic><figDesc>This photo is of the character, Shuri, working in her labratory in the film. We'd like to note the author's caption for the picture "My girl Shuri, a teen tech genius".</figDesc></figure> <!-- We beleive that this picture was important to include considering Shuri's character has had an impact on the author and many others. It is rare to see a strong, intellegent, and independent black character that is interesed in technology. That is why the black community has used a variety of platforms to express their astonishment of the representation in this film.  -->
<p>
  “<orgName>Marvel</orgName> currently has the eyeballs of hundreds of millions of moviegoers across the globe — something that’s never been true before for any comics company. It has a massive platform to tell all those viewers across the planet,” wrote <orgName>Vulture</orgName>. “<seg type="black-representation">‘Anyone can be a hero, regardless of race</seg>, gender, sexual orientation, or anything else.’ It’s not as if <orgName>Marvel</orgName> hasn’t tried and succeeded wildly in getting that very message across in the past.”
</p>
<p>
  <orgName>The Marvel Cinematic Universe</orgName> has finally made good on this potential. I could look at the ad for Black Panther and <seg type="black-representation">actually choose between multiple people I wanted to be</seg>: <persName>King T’Challa</persName>, calm and cool, towering above a group of women and men with varying skin tones and <seg type="black-hair">natural hair</seg>. There’s <persName>Nakia</persName> and <persName>Okoye</persName>, both of <seg type="black-representation">darker skin than most <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>black</desc></trait> women I see on screen</seg>, both independent and strong; and <persName>Shuri</persName>, a certifiable badass with <seg type="black-hair">amazing hair</seg> and smarts and — I could go on. Even <persName>Killmonger</persName>, <seg type="black-hair">his hair in dreadlocks</seg>, has a style I wanted to cop.
</p> <!-- The black hair analysis tag was used considering the attention that the author and many others using digital platforms paid to the natural black hairstyles that the characters wore. People took to social media to admire the black hairstyles of the characters of Black Panther. It was quite admirable considering the lack of natural black hairstyles worn by black characters (usually straight, natural curl pattern is not worn). -->
<p>
  For the first time, <seg type="black-representation">I watched a superhero movie without feeling so personally detached from it</seg>. I now want more than to look like <persName xml:id="LUN">Lupita N’yongo’s</persName> <persName>Nakia</persName>. I want to be her: a strong polyglot who laughs at the idea of settling down with <persName>T’Challa</persName>. Becoming <persName>Nakia</persName> (or some snarky, nap-prone, Allegra-style version of her) seems a whole lot more plausible to me than becoming <persName>Black Widow</persName> or, heck, <orgName>DC’s</orgName> <persName>Wonder Woman</persName>. In her I see the <trait type="place"><label>country</label><desc>African</desc></trait> <seg type="celebration-of-blackness">cultural tenets I admire in my female relatives: fierce loyalty, a lack of physical self-consciousness and tenacity</seg>. It’s not that those other <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>white or non-black</desc></trait> women lack those; it’s that with <persName>Nakia</persName>, there’s an <seg type="black-representation">intimate specificity I’ve never gotten to see before.</seg>
</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/_osZ4DgWYeLjFlN6O7yIlEmSNsg=/0x0:6000x4000/720x0/filters:focal(0x0:6000x4000):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/9546373/BlackPanther596d2f0f45777.jpg"></graphic><figDesc>This photo is of three characters: Nakia, T'Challa, and Okoye. The stand together looking over a balcony in this scene. We would also like to note the author's caption for this picture "Look at the hair on this crew".</figDesc></figure> <!-- We believe that encoding these three photos was important considering how the author commented on them through the captions. She adknowledged the amount of black representation and black hair styles through these captions like many others have using many different digital platforms.   -->
<p>
  That kind of representation is meaningful. It may have taken <orgName>Marvel</orgName> more than four years to embrace its power to shirk Hollywood convention, but Black Panther is literally paying out in dividends. People of color are galvanizing around this film, from superhero-loving kids to <seg type="black-representation">older fans who’ve waited a long time for a movie like this</seg>. It’s now clearer than ever that <seg type="black-representation"> a film starring a majority-black cast</seg> (and set in an empowered African nation, no less) doesn’t have to be a box office disappointment or a niche success. The right movie can become a cultural phenomenon.
</p>
<p>
  <roleName>Director</roleName> <persName xml:id="RC">Ryan Coogler’s</persName> fellow <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>black</desc></trait> filmmakers are also heralding him as a history-bound prodigal son. <name role="director" type="person" ref="RC">Coogler</name> managed to <seg type="black-representation">translate his inherently <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>black</desc></trait> stories into a big-picture world where they rarely get to exist</seg>. It’s encouraging to viewers, and it’s inspiring to his forebears.
</p>
<p>
  “We all have our own version of [a <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>black</desc></trait> superhero movie], I’m sure,” said <persName xml:id="LD">Lee Daniels</persName>, one of just four African-American men to be nominated for a Best Director Oscar, in a recent <orgName>Hollywood Reporter</orgName> roundtable about Hollywood’s slow embrace of <trait type="physical"><label>race</label><desc>black</desc></trait> filmmaking. “And he has paved the way now.”
</p>
<p>
  We can’t ignore the impact Black Panther is having and will continue to have. I know that the viewers still chanting “<placeName>Wakanda</placeName> forever!” won’t stop any time soon. Here’s hoping that Hollywood won’t, either.
</p>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
