<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Twitter Thread: African Tribes and Cultures featured in the Film Black Panther</title>
            <title type="sub">Digital Edition</title>
            <author>
              <persName xml:id="JLU">
                <forename>Jessica</forename>
                <surname>Lu</surname>
                </persName>
              <orgName xml:id="AADHum">African American History, Culture, an Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHum</abbr>)Initiative</orgName>
              </author>
              <respStmt>
                <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                <persName xml:id="SC">
                  <forename>Sophia</forename>
                  <surname>Crooks</surname>
                  </persName>
                <persName xml:id="KG">
                  <forename>Kayla</forename>
                  <surname>Graham</surname>
                  </persName>
                  </respStmt>
                  <respStmt>
                    <resp>Original text transcribed by</resp>
                    <persName ref="#SC">
<forename>Sophia</forename>
<surname>Crooks</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <persName ref="#KG">
<forename>Kayla</forename>
<surname>Graham</surname>
                    </persName>
                    </respStmt>
                    <respStmt>
                <resp>Original TEI template provided by</resp>
                <persName xml:id="RAFF">
                  <forename>Raffaele</forename>
                <surname>Viglianti</surname>
              </persName>
                <orgName xml:id="MITH">Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (<abbr>MITH</abbr>)</orgName>
              </respStmt>
                <funder>
                  <orgName xml:id="MELLON">Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</orgName>
                <orgName xml:id="FIRE">First-Year Innovation and Research Experience (<abbr>FIRE</abbr>)</orgName>
              </funder>
         </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition n="1">First Edition</edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <extent>
            <measure unit="tweets" quantity="28">28 of the tweets in the thread were encoded.</measure>
          </extent>
         <publicationStmt>
          <publisher>
<orgName ref="#AADHum">African American History, Culture, and Digital Humanities (<abbr>AADHum</abbr>) Initiative</orgName>
          </publisher>
          <pubPlace>
<settlement>College Park</settlement>
<region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
          </pubPlace>
          <date when="2018-04-09">April 9, 2018</date>
          <availability status="free">
            <p>In the public domain.</p>
          </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
           <seriesStmt>
             <title type="main">Encoding for Black Lives: Legacies of Resistance and Reinvention in the (Re)Making of Black Freedom Online</title>
             <title type="sub">Black Panther</title>
             <respStmt>
               <resp>Edited by</resp>
               <persName ref="#JLU">
                 <forename>Jessica</forename>
                 <surname>Lu</surname>
               </persName>
             </respStmt>
             <respStmt>
               <resp>Texts identified and assembled by</resp>
               <persName ref="#SC">
                 <forename>Sophia</forename>
                 <surname>Crooks</surname>
                 <persName ref="#KG">
<forename>Kayla</forename>
<surname>Graham</surname>
                 </persName>
               </persName>
             </respStmt>
           </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
            <bibl>
<title>Thread on African tribes/cultures featured in #BlackPanther. #Wakanda</title>
<author>
  @diasporicblues
<note>This is a twitter handle.</note>
</author>
<publisher>
  <orgName xml:id="TWIT">Twitter.com</orgName>
</publisher>
<pubPlace ref="https://twitter.com/diasporicblues/status/964770975190528000?s=12">
  Twitter.com
  <note>This is a Black place considering many twitter users are Black and use "Black Twitter" as a way to express their beliefs, feelings, and attitudes towards different aspects of the world around them.</note>
</pubPlace>
<date when="2018-02-17">February 17, 2018</date>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="JLUDISS">
      <title type="main">Reckoning with Freedom</title>
      <title type="sub">Legacies of Exclusion, Dehumanization, and Black Resistance in the Rhetoric of the Freedmen's Bureau</title>
      <author>
        <persName ref="#JLU">
          <forename>Jessica</forename>
          <surname>Lu</surname>
             </persName>
           </author>
            <publisher>
              <orgName xml:id="UMD">University of Maryland</orgName>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>
              <settlement>College Park</settlement>
              <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </pubPlace>
             <date when="2018-06-28">28 June 2018</date>
           </bibl>
           <bibl>
             <interpGrp resp="#LUDISS" type="freedom-ideas">
               <desc>Ideational analysis of freedom.</desc>
               <interp xml:id="STRAND1">Strand 1</interp>
               <interp xml:id="STRAND2">Strand 2</interp>
               <interp xml:id="STRAND3">Strand 3</interp>
               <interp xml:id="STRAND4">Strand 4</interp>
               <interp xml:id="STRAND5">Strand 5</interp>
             </interpGrp>
           </bibl>
            </listBibl>
            <biblStruct type="article">
              <analytic>
              <author>
              <persName xml:id="CKS">
              <forename>Catherine</forename>
              <surname>Knight Steele</surname>
              </persName>
              </author>
              <title>The Digital Barbershop: Blogs and Online Oral Culture Within the African American Community</title>
              </analytic>
              <monogr>
              <title level="j">SAGE journals</title>
              <imprint>
              <publisher>University of Maryland Department of Communications</publisher>
              <pubPlace>
              <settlement>College Park</settlement>
              <region>Maryland (<abbr>MD</abbr>)</region>
              <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
              </pubPlace>
              <date when="2016-12-01">December 1, 2016</date>
              </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <note>In this article, Catherine Knight Steele explores nine blogs by various African Americans in order to analyze the rhetorical strategies they use. She found that online spaces have become comparable to Black barbershops and beauty shops in that Black people have begun to use the same rhetorical strategies they have used in the past. Black people use these blogs to crtique aspects scoiety as well as assert their Blackness. The comparison of online platforms as Black barbershops and beauty shops contributes to this digital edition project considering an immense amount of effort has been made to amplify Black twitter users, bloggers, and Youtubers. The language used to describe the Black Panther movie, specifically the language used to describe the impact of a movie that centralizes accurate representations of Black people has been mplified in this project. </note>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct type="article">
            <analytic>
            <author>
            <persName ref="#CKS">
            <forename>Catherine</forename>
            <surname>Knight Steele</surname>
            </persName>
            <persName ref="#JLU">
            <forename>Jessica</forename>
            <surname>Lu</surname>
            </persName>
            </author>
            <title>Defying Death: Black Joy as Resistance Online</title>
            </analytic>
            <monogr>
              <title type="j">Taylor and Francis Group</title>
              <imprint>
            <publisher></publisher>
            <pubPlace>
            <settlement>New York</settlement>
            <region></region>
            <country>United States of America (<abbr>USA</abbr>)</country>
            </pubPlace>
            <date when="2018-05-01">May 1, 2018</date>
              </imprint>
              </monogr>
              <note>In this article, Catherine Knight Steele and Jessica Lu explore the rhetoric used by Black twitter users. They found that various hastags, memes, and other practices have been used by Black people as a form of resistance. This resistance stems from the lack of postive representation that Black people recieve in film and the media in general. The portrayals of Black joy online has been used to humanize Black people. This contributes to the project considering we have focused on amlifying and perserving the postive rhetoric throughout online spaces used to describe the Black Panther movie. The response from Black people after the release of this movie exemplifies the fact that Blackness does not always have to correlate to sadness and death but rather intellegence, technological adnvancement, and strength. </note>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
          <hyphenation eol="none">
            <p>Except where normalization disrupts the formatting of the digital surrogate when rendered online, all end-of-line hyphenation in the original source material has been reformed. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>orig</gi> and <gi>reg</gi> elements giving the original hyphenation and regularized version, respectively.</p>
          </hyphenation>
          <normalization method="markup">
            <p>All obvious spelling and typographical errors in the original source material is corrected. The <gi>choice</gi> element has been used to enclose <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements giving the original error and correction, respectively.</p>
          </normalization>
          <normalization method="silent">
            <p>Whenever necessary, spacing between words and following punctuation has been regularized to zero spaces; spacing between words has been regularized to one space.</p>
          </normalization>
          <normalization source="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/05/15/the-case-for-black-english">
            <p>Instances of African American Vernacular English have purposefully NOT been adjusted to comply with American English language practices. African American Vernacular English is wholly valid in its form, features, and creativity, despite the dominance and presumed correctness of American English.</p>      </normalization>      <p>To represent changes and/or corrections made by the original source authors BEFORE the encoding process, encoders use <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>subst</gi>.</p>
            <p>Encoding includes the use of <gi>supplied</gi> to provide clarificationand supporting content, including out-links to relevant digital content and citations of Black and Black-centric academic research.</p>
            <normalization>
                <p>Hashtags (#Wakanda and #BlackPanther) have been retained at the end of each tweet to emphasize the goal of the author who wrote this tweet thread. The author hoped to reach a wide range of people so that her work could be viewed by many in order to encourage conversation about African culture, tribes, and traditions depicted in Black Panther.</p>
                <p>The emojis used in the tweet thread to show the flag of the African country that some of the characters come from has been omitted. This was done because we believe that it is not important to the actual content or importance of the text. Also, TEI has very little tags that allow for emojis to be encoded.</p> <!-- TEI might want to consider adding new tags in order to make it easier for people to encode digital texts that include things like emojis, videos, pictures, hyperlinks, etc. -->
            </normalization>
          </editorialDecl>
          <samplingDecl>
        <p>Only one or two pictures were encoded from each tweet in the thread using the appropriate TEI tags. This is due to the fact that only one picture showing an aspect of African culture decpicted in Black Panther along with one picture showing African culture in the real world is sufficient enough to develop an understanding about what the author is describing in each tweet.</p>
        <p>28 out of the 28 tweets in the thread were encoded because they were all important in terms of exemplifying the attention that was paid to accurately representing African tribes. However, none of the comments under the tweet were encoded because we believe that some of them are not important to the focus of our projet which is the impact of the representation in Black Panther.</p>
        <p>The amount of retweets and likes of the first tweet in the thread was retained. We beleive it wass important to emphasize the popularity of this thread to point out that Twitter is a Black place in which Black twitter users interact together to provide their thoughts and feelings towards different events.</p>
          </samplingDecl>
<projectDesc>
<p>This project seeks to identify, collect, preserve, and analyze FREEDOM discourse, as constituted and argued by Black users online. Directed by Dr. Jessica H. Lu, this project is currently being advanced by several undergraduatestudents at the University of Maryland, College Park: Sophia Crooks, Kayla Graham, Kaanita Iyer, Ariana Lawson, Alice Liu, and Courtney Richardson.</p>
<p>This thread was encoded because it exemplifies the celebration of blackness. Black Twitter users are excited about the celebration of Black, specifically African culture and tradtions that were depicted in the Black Panther movie. These people used Twitter as a digital space to discuss aspects of their culture.</p>
  </projectDesc>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
    <langUsage>
      <language ident="AAVE">African American Vernacular English</language> <!--AAVE is purposefully listed first, to visually reinforce its validity alongside Standard American English and primacy among Black Americans. -->
      <language ident="us-en">Standard American English</language>
    </langUsage>
    <particDesc>
      <listOrg>
<org>
<orgName xml:id="VAT">Various African tribes</orgName>
<note>There were several African tribes amplified throughout this digital surrogate. Each tribe deserves to be amplified seperately which is why they were all given seperate xmi ids in the body of the text. The tribes are not listed seperately here but rather as a larger group because their information on the Library of Congress does not exist. This is due to the the erasure of Black people. However, we still beleive it is important that the African tribes in this film be recognized considering so many of them were represented in this film through the costumes, hair styles, makeup, and cultural customs of the characters.</note>
</org>
      </listOrg>
      <listPerson>
<person>
<persName xml:id="RUC" ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no92026494">
<forename>Ruth</forename>
<surname>Carter</surname>
</persName>
<idno type="LCAF">no92026494</idno>
<note>Ruth Carter along with Hannah Beachler were costume designers who worked to create the Afrocentric costumes for the Black Panther film. Ruth as a Black woman costume designer was extremely important to the film because she did an amazing job at providing so much representation from multiple African tribes.</note>
</person>
<person>
  <persName xml:id="HAB">
<forename>Hannah</forename>
<surname>Beachler</surname>
  </persName>
  <note>Hannah Beachler along with Ruth Carter were costume designers who worked to create the Afrocentric costumes for the Black Panther film. She also did an amazing job at providing representation in the film and making sure the costumes that the characters wore were accurate. Her Library of Congress information is not listed simply because it does not exist. This emphasizes the fact that many Black people, but specifically Black women in particular have been silenced.</note>
</person>
<person>
<persName xml:id="DAG" ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008162135">
<forename>Danai</forename>
<surname>Gurira</surname>
</persName>
<idno type="LCAF">no2008162135</idno>
<note>Danai Gurira is an actress and she played Okoye in Black Panther. She along with many of the other Black women in this film provided representation that was very needed; Black women as strong, independent, intellegent beings.</note>
</person>
<person>
<persName xml:id="LUN" ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009107748">
<forename>Lupita</forename>
<surname>Nyong'o</surname>
</persName>
<idno type="LCAF">no2009107748</idno>
<note>Lupita Nyong'o is an actress and model. She starred in Black Panther as Nakia in Black Panther. Herself along with Letita Wright, Angela Basset, and Danai Gurira portrayed strong, intellgent, and independent Black women in this film. Lupita is important for this project because she was important for a alot of Black women who had been waiting for this type of representation in film. Many Black women took to twitter to describe her character and how it impacted them.</note>
</person>
      </listPerson>
      </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
<listChange>
<change>The B in Black was capitalized throughout the text to amplify Black people, made on
<date when="2018-11-09">November 9, 2018</date>.
</change>
<change>One or more pictures from each tweet containing more than two pictures were removed because only one picture from the moive as well as one from the real world was sufficient enough to understand the author's purpose of the tweet, made on
<date when="2018-04-09">April 9, 2018</date>.
</change>
</listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<div>
         <p><supplied source="http://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/2056305116683205"><supplied source="https://www.taylorfrancis.com/books/e/9781351784122/chapters/10.4324%2F9781315202129-9">Thread on African tribes/cultures featured in #BlackPanther. #Wakanda</supplied></supplied></p>
         <p>41,132 Retweets 55,784 Likes</p> <!-- We choose to include the number of retweets and likes for the opening tweet of this thread to emphasize the impact that this tweet thread has had on the Twitter community.  Many people have viewed this thread, interacted with it, and agreed with many aspects of it. The popularity of this twitter thread emphasizes the use of digital spaces by the black community to make connections. The black community is able to use digital spaces such as social media platforms to talk with other members of the community. These digital spaces provide black twitter users with a place to discuss different events that have affected and continue to affect the black community. --> <!--The date in which we encoded the retweets and likes was April 23, 2018 (these numbers change so it is important to indicate the date when these numbers were encoded) -->
</div>
         <div>
<p><orgName xml:id="MUR">Mursi</orgName> and <orgName xml:id="SUR">Surma</orgName> Lip Plates. Lip plates or disks are a form of ceremonial body modification. While many cultures use them they're best known by the <orgName>Surma</orgName> and <orgName>Mursi</orgName> tribes in <country xml:id="ETH" type="nation">Ethiopia</country>. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/10264335/Black_Panther__film__123.jpg"/><figDesc>This figure depicts characters of a specific tribe in the movie Black Panther. The tribe leader wears a Surma or Mursi lip plate as described by the author of this tweet thread.</figDesc></figure>
<figure><graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DWOPGANVMAAV8n-.jpg"/><figDesc>This picture is of a women who belongs to an actual Surma or Mursi tribe in Ethiopia. She wears a lip plate which is simliar to the tribe leader character in the movie.</figDesc></figure> <!-- We decided to encode the pictures used by the author of this markup in order to show how much attention was put into retaining African culture in the movie. People can view the pictures from the movie alongside pictures from real life and make comparisons. Africans or African Americans can also view the pictures and see themslves represented within the film.</!-->
         <div>
<p><orgName xml:id="ZUL">Zulu</orgName> headdress. <persName xml:id="QROM">Queen Ramonda</persName> wears a distinct headdress. It's reminiscent of the reed <orgName>Zulu</orgName> flared hats or "Isicholos." The <orgName>Zulu</orgName> headdresses are traditionally worn by married women for ceremonial celebrations.</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://vergehub.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/Zulu-headdress.jpg"/><figDesc>This picture is a collage of four different pictures. Two of the pictures show the character, Queen Romonda, wearing a traditional Zulu headdress in the film. The other two pictures show two real life women who wear the "Isicholos". </figDesc></figure>
         </div>
         <div>
<p>Many of the costumes have unique and futuristic ornamentation and details. These were made by emulating styles of the <orgName xml:id="MAAS"><choice><orig>Masai people</orig> <corr>Maasai people</corr></choice></orgName>. The <orgName>Maasai people</orgName> of East Africa live in southern <country>Kenya</country> and northern <country xml:id="TAN">Tanzania</country>. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p> <!-- We choose to correct the spelling of the name of the tribe so that people that view our website are given accurate information regarding the spelling of the tribe described in this tweet thread. Providing people with accurate information pertaining to non-white populations is especially important considering not much attention is given to making sure accurate information is spread about people of color i.e. continuation of black sterotypes, the Christoper Columbus narrative, the portrayal African countries as unstable and in need of "saviors". -->
<figure><graphic url="https://static.pulse.ng/img/incoming/origs8001409/6319721768-w900-h600/DWOQtIRUMAAOs3k.jpg"/><figDesc>This picture depicts the "futuristic" costumes worn by some of the characters in the movie.</figDesc></figure>
<figure><graphic url="https://zoede.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/maasai-warriors-dora-milaje-black-panther-african-influences-zoedeblog.jpg"/><figDesc>This picture is of a group of actual Maasai people. It can be seen that the costumes used in the film were influenced by the tradtional attire of this group of people.</figDesc></figure>
         </div>
         <div>
<p><orgName xml:id="IGB">Igbo</orgName> Mask. In one scene <persName xml:id="EKILL">Erik Killmonger</persName> wears a mask. The masks, known as Mgbedike, are distinguished by the large size and bold masculine features. They are used in <orgName>Igbo</orgName> rituals and are designed to contrast the female dancers with their more feminine beauty. #BlackPanther</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://pixel.nymag.com/imgs/daily/vulture/2017/06/09/black-panther-breakdown-1/black-panther-14.nocrop.w710.h2147483647.2x.png"/><figDesc>This picture shows the character, Erik Killmonger, wearing a tradtional Igbo Mask.</figDesc></figure>
<figure><graphic url="https://lists.ng/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/Mgbedike.jpg"/><figDesc>This picure shows a side-by-side of Erik Killmonger wearing an Igbo mask in the movie and an actual Igbo mask that has been displayed in what looks like a museuem.</figDesc></figure>
         </div>
         <div>
<p>Basotho Blanket. In several scenes, <persName xml:id="WKA">W'Kabi</persName> <persName xml:id="DKA">(Daniel Kaluuya)</persName> and others are shown wearing Basotho blankets around their necks. Though the blankets are originally from the <orgName xml:id="LES">Lesotho people</orgName> the designs are synonymous with the <orgName xml:id="SES">Sesotho people</orgName>. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="http://atlantablackstar.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/pjimage-8-1-600x257.jpg" /><figDesc>This picture is a collage made up of three different pictures. one of the pictures shows the character, W'Kabi, wearing an article of clothing that is simliar to a Basotho blanket. The other two photos show two other men who wear the Basotho blanket in the real world.</figDesc></figure>
         </div>
         <div>
<p><orgName xml:id="NDE">Ndebele</orgName> Neck Rings. <persName xml:id="SHU">Shuri</persName> and the <persName xml:id="DMI">Dora Milaje</persName> have outfits with a prominent collar. The <orgName>South Ndebele peoples</orgName> of <country xml:id="ZIM">Zimbabwe</country> and <country xml:id="SAF">South Africa</country> wear neck rings as part of their traditional dress and as a sign of wealth and status. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://static.pulse.ng/img/incoming/origs8001418/9599724726-w900-h600/DWOTZm8VQAA2bOd.jpg"/><figDesc>This photo is of the character, Dora Milaje, wearing a costume with a "prominent collar" which is similar to the tradtitonal Ndebele neck rings.</figDesc></figure>
<figure><graphic url="http://media.gettyimages.com/photos/ndebele-woman-wearing-a-traditional-costume-and-idzilla-bronze-or-picture-id640237073?s=594x594"/><figDesc>This photo is of a women wearing tradtional Ndebele neck rings.</figDesc></figure>
         </div>
         <div>
<p>Many of the costumes have a distinctive red earthy tone. This was done by studying the colors used by the <orgName xml:id="HIM">Himba people</orgName> of <country><offset><choice><orig>north-western</orig> <corr>North Western</corr></choice></offset>Namibia</country>. <orgName>Himba people</orgName> are known for applying a red ochre paste, known as "otjize", to their skin and hair. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="http://atlantablackstar.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/pjimage-4-2-600x257.jpg"/><figDesc>This collage shows all three of the pictures used by the author to depict the Himba people of North Western Namibia. One picture shows a tribe leader in the film who has applied red ochre paste like the two women in the other two photos who use "otjize" on their skin and hair in real life.</figDesc></figure><!-- A collage of all or some of the pictures used by the author of the thread were encoded if found. A lot of the pictures that the author used sepaterely in the tweets were grouped together as collages when we were searching for the photos on Google Images. -->
         </div>
         <div>
<p><persName xml:id="FWH">Forest Whittaker</persName> plays shaman <persName xml:id="ZUR">Zuri</persName> who's the spiritual leader of <placeName>Wakanda</placeName>. He wears ornate flowing robes known as an Agbada. It's one of the names for a flowing <choice><orig>wide-sleeved</orig><reg>wide sleeved</reg></choice> robe worn by men/women in much of <placeName> <bloc type="sub-continent">West Africa</bloc></placeName> ,and <placeName><bloc type="sub-continent">North Africa</bloc></placeName>. #BlackPanther  #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="http://www.thenightowlmama.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/BlackPanther-attire.jpg"/><figDesc>This image is of the character, shaman Zuri, along with another character in the film. They both wear costumes that resemble traditional Agbada.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p>There was a lot of inspiration taken from the <orgName xml:id="DOG">Dogon</orgName>people. They live in the central plateau region of <country xml:id="MAL" type="nation">Mali</country>, in <placeName><bloc type="sub-continent">West Africa</bloc></placeName>. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/03/Dogon12.jpg"/><figDesc>This is an image of three Dogon men in their ceremonial attire, which influenced many of Black Panther costumes.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p><orgName xml:id="TUA">Tuareg</orgName>scarfs. Several characters in the film wear large scarves covering their head and face. These are similar to the ones worn by the <orgName>Tuareg</orgName> people. The <orgName>Tuareg</orgName> people inhabit an area in <placeName> <bloc type="sub-continents">North and West Africa</bloc></placeName>. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.kenyabuzz.com/lifestyle/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/IMG_2943.png"/><figDesc>This is a collage of all four of the pictures that they author used to match her description of the Tuareg scarf. One of the pictures is a screenshoot from the Black Panther movie which contains characters wearing Tuareg scarfs. The other three pictures show men and women in real life wearing the Tuareg scarf.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p>Other tribes of sartorial inspiration were the <orgName xml:id="TUR">Turkana</orgName> people in <country xml:id="KEN" type="nation">Kenya</country>. #BlackPanther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://static.pulse.ng/img/incoming/origs8001425/4929721774-w900-h600/DWOcqBvVwAES3EJ.jpg"/><figDesc>This picture is of three women from the Turkana tribe in Kenya wearing large beaded neck rings which inspired the creation of some of the costumes in the film.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p>The language spoken in #Wakanda  is <lang xml:lang="Xhosa">Xhosa</lang>, a language spoken by over 19 million people in <placeName> <bloc type="sub-continent">Southern Africa</bloc></placeName>.</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://twitter.com/diasporicblues/status/964789030369087488"/><figDesc>This is a map of South Africa that has shaded percentages of how many people speak the Xhosa language, the primary language used by African characters in the film.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> <persName ref="#DAG">Danai Gurira</persName> is from <country>Zimbabwe</country></p>
<figure><graphic url="https://pursuenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Danai-Gurira-as-Okoye-in-Black-Panther.jpg"/><figDesc>This is photo of Danai Gurira as her character, Okoye during one of the scenes in the film.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> <persName xml:id="FLK">Florence Kasumba</persName> is from <country xml:id="UGA">Uganda</country></p>
<figure><graphic url="https://pixel.nymag.com/imgs/daily/vulture/2018/02/16/16-florence-kasumba.w710.h473.jpg"/><figDesc>Pictured here is screenshot of Florence Kasumba as the charcter, Ayo in her Wakandan military uniform.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> <persName>Daniel Kaluuya</persName> is from <country>Uganda</country></p>
<figure><graphic url="http://mamasmission.simpliolabs.netdna-cdn.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/Daniel-Kaluuya-Black-Panther-Training-800x533.jpg"/><figDesc>This is a screenshoot from the film. Daniel Kaluuya iss seen acting as the character W'Kabi while wearing his traditonal attire.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> <persName ref="#LUN">Lupita Nyong'o</persName> is from <country>Kenya</country></p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.cinematographe.it/wp-content/uploads/2018/01/lupita-nyongo-black-panther-combattimenti-2-696x392.jpg"/><figDesc>Here is a photo of Lupita Nyong'o as the charcter Nakia dressed in an Wakandan miltary uniform.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> <persName xml:id="JOK">John Kani</persName> is from <country>South Africa</country></p>
<figure><graphic url="http://ostudiopost.co.za/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/TChaka-Touches-TChalla-Marvel.jpg"/><figDesc>This is a headshot of T'chaka played by the South African actor John Kani.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p>Did y'all catch when our sis <persName ref="#LUN">Lupita</persName>begins the film fighting for enslaved girls in <country xml:id="NIG">Nigeria</country>. <persName ref="#LUN">Lupita</persName> learned to speak <lang xml:lang="HAU">Hausa</lang> for certain scenes in the film. She also trained in judo, jujitsu, silat and Filipino martial arts.</p> <!-- We have decieded to keep the words "y'all" and "sis" to preserve the African American vernacular used in this thread. -->
</div>
        <div>
<p> <persName xml:id="MBJ">Michael B. Jordan</persName>'s bumpy, ritualistic tribal markings on his chest and torse resemble the scar tattoos of the <orgName>Mursi</orgName> and <orgName>Surma</orgName> tribes in <country>Ethiopia</country>. #Black Panther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.cinematographe.it/wp-content/uploads/2017/06/michael-b-jordan-black-panther-killmonger.jpg"/><figDesc>This is an image of Michael B Jordan as Erik Killmonger who has bumpy tribal markings all over his torso and chest.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> <persName xml:id="TCH">T'Challa</persName>'s Kente scarf. Kente, known as nwentom in <lang xml:lang="AKA">Akan</lang>, is a type of silk and cotton fabric made of interwoven cloth strips and is native to the <orgName xml:id="AKA">Akan</orgName> people of <country xml:id="GHA">Ghana</country>.#BlackPanther #Wakanda </p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.ghanacrusader.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/bp-kente.jpg"/><figDesc>Here is a collage of photos that include two images of T'Challa, played by Chadwick Boseman, wearing a Kente scarf around his neck as well as photos of Africans in the real world wearing Kente fabric.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p><seg type="celebration-of-blackness">The Black women who spent months researching and making #Wakanda come to life.</seg> <persName ref="#RUC">Ruth Carter</persName> - costume designer and <persName ref="#HAB">Hannah Beachler</persName> - production designer. #Black Panther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://media.pri.org/s3fs-public/styles/original_image/public/embed/2018/02/BP_embed_1_RuthCarter1.jpeg?itok=5IJHSMYc"/><figDesc>This is a picture of the costume designer for Black Panther, Ruth E. Carter, standing in what looks like a studio in which she designed the costumes for the characters in Black Panther.</figDesc></figure>
<figure><graphic url="https://vignette4.wikia.nocookie.net/marvelcinematicuniverse/images/7/7d/Hannah_Beachler.jpg/revision/latest/scale-to-width-down/350?cb=20160918105602" /><figDesc>Pictured here is Hannah Beachler, the production designer for Black Panther, on the red carpet.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p>Did y'all hear this song? <choice><orig>Its</orig><corr>It's</corr></choice>from <country>South Africa</country>. <persName xml:id="BAW">Babes wodumo</persName> ft <persName xml:id="MAW">Mamointsha - Wololo</persName> #Black Panther #Wakanda</p>
<figure><media mimeType="video" url="https://youtu.be/hlkybvVEQ4g"><desc>This is 3 minute and 56 second music video of the song Babes wodumo Ft Mampintsha - Wololo which was played during the film.</desc></media></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p><seg type="celebration-of-blackness">Can we take a moment to appreciate how Africans across the continent came out for #Black Panther movie premiere!</seg> This is <settlement xml:id="LAG">Lagos</settlement> <country>Nigeria</country>. #Wakanda </p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.ossifymedia.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/Black-Panther-Premiere-Nigeria.png"/><figDesc>In this picture there four Black people in traditonal African attire at the premiere of Black Panther in Lagos, Nigeria.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> #BlackPanther movie premiere in <settlement>Kisumu</settlement>, <country>Kenya</country>. #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://twitter.com/diasporicblues/status/964932021398142976"/><figDesc>Pictued here are four Black people in traditional African attire attending the Black Panther premiere in Kissumu, Kenya.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> The <placeName xml:id="GRV">Great Rift Valley</placeName>. Scientists have estimated that the <placeName>Great Rift Valley</placeName> found in <country>Kenya</country> was formed over 20 million years ago when the Earth's crust began to split. #BlackPanther #Wakanda </p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.rovos.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/01/zulu-in-valley.jpg"/><figDesc>This is a picture of a man standing on a cliff overlooking the Great Rift Valley in Kenya. This valley shows similarities to the valley of Wakanda in the film.</figDesc></figure>
<figure><graphic url="https://cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/sAN6k0miIlApLokP_YD0OvJi2UI=/0x0:1688x950/1600x900/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_image/image/55840269/BlackPanther_Poster_Lg.0.jpg"/><figDesc>This is a picture is taken from the Black Panther poster. The author has cut the bottom of the poster off to emphasize the character, Black Panther, standing on the Black Panther shaped cliff of Wakanda. This cliff and the view from it resemble the Great Rift Valley of Kenya.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
        <div>
<p> Tribal <choice><orig>make-up</orig><reg>makeup</reg></choice> is practiced in many African tribes.The <choice><orig>make-up</orig><reg>makeup</reg></choice>, often in the form of face paint, is used for many different reasons and can signify many different things such as hunting, religious and traditional reasons, military purposes or to scare an enemy. #BlackPanther</p>
<figure><graphic url="http://media.comicbook.com/2017/06/black-panther-shuri-1001960-1280x0.jpg"/><figDesc>This is an image of Letitia Wright as the charcter Shuri, who wears paint on her face, very simliar to tribal makeup used by African tribes.</figDesc></figure>
        </div>
    <div>
<p> #BlackPanther was totally a <seg type="celebration-of-blackness">Afrocentric natural hair movie</seg>. Inspiration came from this collection of <choice><orig>black</orig><reg>Black</reg></choice> hairstyles shot by the Nigerian photographer <persName xml:id="JDOO">J.D. ’Okhai Ojeikere</persName>. #Wakanda</p>
<figure><graphic url="https://www.artsy.net/artist/jd-okhai-ojeikere"/><figDesc>This is a picture of girl with a natural Black hairstyle which was included in the collection of photos by the Nigerian photographer J. D. ’Okhai Ojeikere.</figDesc></figure>
  </div>
</div>
  </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
